A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia Board of Dentistry, 2012-2014.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Minutes of the Virginia Board of Dentistry,
2012-2014.
The Library of Virginia
54118
Virginia. Dept. of Health Professions.
.7 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions
Acquisition Information
Accession 54118 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 02/05/2024.
Historical Information
Regulation of the health professions began late in the nineteenth century. On January 31, 1884, the General Assembly passed an act creating the Board of Medical Examiners to certify physicians for practice in Virginia. Two years later, acts establishing the Board of Dental Examiners (now the Board of Dentistry) and the Board of Pharmacy were passed by the General Assembly on February 26 and March 3, 1886, respectively. The Board of Embalmers (now the Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers) was created by an act passed on March 5, 1894, and the Board of Veterinary Examiners (now the Board of Veterinary Medicine) was established by an act passed on February 27, 1896. On May 1, 1903, the General Assembly created the Board of Graduate Nurses (now the State Board of Nursing), and on March 11, 1916, the Board of Optometry was established by legislative action.
The Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on March 31, 1977, to provide administrative services to the health regulatory boards of the state. The boards continue to regulate their professions through the examination, licensing, and disciplining of the practitioners of health science. In 1986, the Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards became the Dept. of Health Professions. Its mission is to enhance the delivery of safe and competent health care by licensing qualified health care professionals, enforcing standards of practice, and providing information to both practitioners and consumers of health care services.
Scope and Content
Official minutes and related attachments documenting the meetings, activities, discussions and policy decisions, and recommendations of the Virginia Board of Dentistry. Also includes minutes for Committees and other groups (Credentials Committee, Clinical Exam Advisory Panel, Examination Committee, Executive Committee, Regulatory/Legislative Committee, Nominating Committee, Special Conference Committee, Dental Laboratory Workgroup (2012)), as well as records related to informal conferences, telephone conferences, formal hearings, public hearings, and new board member orientation.
Contents List
- Minutes of the Virginia Board of Dentistry, 2012-2014.
  - Accession 54118 (2012-2014)., Extent: .7 cu. ft.
    Includes original, signed minutes, 2012-2014. Also includes transcripts for the Public Hearing on Sedation and Anesthesia Regulations, 2013; and the Public Hearing on Reorganizing Chapter 20, 2014.
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Jan 6. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Jan 20. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Jan 27. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Credentials Committee, 2012 Jan 27. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Executive Committee, 2012 Mar 8. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - FULL BOARD, 2012 Mar 9. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Mar 30. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Telephone conference call, 2012 Apr 5. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Apr 13. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dental Laboratory Workgroup, 2012 Apr 20. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 May 11. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dental Laboratory Workgroup, 2012 May 18. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Telephone conference call, 2012 May 22. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 May 25. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - FULL BOARD, 2012 June 8. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 June 8. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2012 June 14. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Credentials Committee, 2012 June 15. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 July 13. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 July 20. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Credentials Committee, 2012 July 20. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Telephone conference call, 2012 July 23. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Aug 3. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Telephone conference call, 2012 Aug 22. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Aug 31. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Credentials Committee, 2012 Aug 31. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - New member orientation, 2012 Sept 6. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - FULL BOARD, 2012 Sept 7. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Nominating Committee, 2012 Sept 7. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Formal Hearing, 2012 Sept 7. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2012 Oct 11. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Oct 12. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Oct 26. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Regulatory/Legislative Committee, 2012 Nov 9. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2012 Nov 13. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Nov 16. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2012 Nov 30. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Formal Hearing, 2012 Dec 6. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Executive Committee, 2012 Dec 6. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - FULL BOARD, 2012 Dec 7. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Jan 11. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Telephone conference call, 2013 Jan 16. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Credentials Committee, 2013 Jan 25. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Examination Committee and Clinical Exam Advisory Panel, 2013 Feb 1. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2013 Feb 14. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Mar 1. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - FULL BOARD, 2013 Mar 7. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Executive Committee, 2013 Mar 7. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - FULL BOARD, 2013 Mar 8. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Examination Committee, 2013 Mar 8. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Mar 15. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Mar 29. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2013 Apr 2. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Credentials Committee, 2013 Apr 5. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Apr 12. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2013 Apr 24. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Apr 26. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 May 10. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Credential Conference Committee, 2013 May 17. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Formal Hearing, 2013 June 6. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 June 14. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Credential Committee, 2013 June 14. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 June 21. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 July 12. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 July 19. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Credentials Committee, 2013 July 19. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - New member orientation, 2013 July 26. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Aug 2. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Aug 23. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2013 Aug 29. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Credentials Committee, 2013 Aug 30. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Aug 30. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Formal hearing, 2013 Sept 12. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Nominating Committee, 2013 Sept 13. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - FULL BOARD, 2013 Sept 13. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Sept 20. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2013 Sept 26. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Nov 6. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2013 Nov 6. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2013 Nov 16. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Telephone conference call, 2013 Nov 20. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Credentials Committee, 2013 Nov 22. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - pSpecial Conference Committee, 2013 Nov 22. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Public Hearing on Sedation and Anethesia Regulations, 2013 Nov 8. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - FULL BOARD, 2013 Dec 5. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Regulatory/Legislative Committee, 2013 Dec 5. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Formal hearing, 2013 Dec 6. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Telephone conference call, 2014 Jan 9. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Public Hearing on Reorganizing Chapter 20, 2014 Jan 10. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Jan 10. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Jan 24. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Telephone conference call, 2014 Jan 24. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Credentials Committee, 2014 Jan 31. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Regulatory/Legislative Committee, 2014 Feb 7. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 Mar 6. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - FULL BOARD, 2014 Mar 7. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Mar 21. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Mar 28. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2014 Apr 3. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2014 Apr 23. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Apr 25. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Regulatory/Legislative Committee, 2014 May 2. (Box 2)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 May 9. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - FULL BOARD - Special Session, 2014 May 9. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 May 9. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 June 6. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 June 12. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - FULL BOARD, 2014 June 13. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 June 13. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 June 20. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Credentials Committee, 2014 June 20. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 June 27. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - New member orientation, 2014 July 11. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2014 July 16. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 July 18. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Aug 1. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Aug 8. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2014 Aug 25. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Aug 29. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - New member orientation, 2014 Sept 10. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - FULL BOARD, 2014 Sept 12. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Sept 19. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2014 Sept 30. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Oct 3. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Oct 17. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - FULL BOARD - Business meeting, 2014 Oct 24. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Oct 31. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 Nov 7. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Nov 14. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 Nov 21. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Special Conference Committee, 2014 Dec 5. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Telephone conference call (Special Session), 2014 Dec 9. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Formal hearing, 2014 Dec 11. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - FULL BOARD, 2014 Dec 12. (Box 2, Folder 12)